A Guide to the William Logan Threlkeld Papers, 1919-1972
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
William Logan Threlkeld Papers, 1919-1972
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1975-005
1.0 cu. ft. 2 boxes
Papers of William Logan Threlkeld, professor of zoology and biology at Virginia Polytechnic Institute (1929-1958), including biographical materials, personal and professional correspondence, research files, and printed materials.
Threlkeld, William Logan
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The William Logan Threlkeld Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1975.
Biographical Note
William Logan Threlkeld, the son of Thomas B. and Harriet Taylor Threlkeld, was born in Versailles, Kentucky on August 8, 1893. After obtaining a bachelor's degree in biology and chemistry from Georgetown College, Threlkeld served as assistant principal of a Madisonville, Kentucky high school from 1915 to 1917. He served as a lieutenant in the army during World War I, then worked as an instructor in Michigan (1920-1921), a science teacher at Hargrave Academy (1922-1927), and an instructor and research fellow in biology at the University of Virginia, where he would earn his master's (1929) and doctoral (1934) degrees in parasitology. In 1929, Threlkeld was hired as an assistant professor of zoology and biology at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. In 1938, he was named associate professor; in 1957, professor. Following his 1958 retirement from VPI, Threlkeld worked as a professor of biology at Milligan College from 1959 to 1961 and at Shorter College from 1961 to 1964. He married Carrie Louise Vaden (1898-1994) in 1924, and the couple had three children. William L. Threlkeld died in June, 1988 and was buried in Chatham Burial Park, Chatham (Pittsylvania County), Virginia.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the papers of William Logan Threlkeld, professor of zoology and biology at Virginia Polytechnic Institute from 1929 to 1958. The collection contains biographical materials, personal and professional correspondence, research files, and printed materials.
Though there is much overlap between the personal and professional correspondence, letters of a predominantly personal nature from family members, aquaintances, former teachers, and former students, are found at the beginning of the collection. Also from Threlkeld's personal life is a collection of materials relating to various awards and memberships, as well as his military service. A folder of biographical materials contains a booklet about the Threlkeld School, operated by Threlkeld's father; a 1929 biology exam book from University of Virginia; a bibliography of Threlkeld's works; and various biographical sketches. Also relating to Threlkeld's personal life is material on the honor society of Sigma Xi. The collection also contains numerous opinion pieces written by Threlkeld, a number of them in the form of letters written to newspapers and political figures and largely focused on communism. Accompanying these pieces is a small collection of printed materials reflecting Threlkeld's political views.
From Threlkeld's professional career, the collection contains several subject files relating to both his scientific research and his work for the Virginia Cooperative Extension Service. Included are project folders on parasites in cattle, sheep, and swine, with a particular emphasis on the relationship between cobalt deficiency and the presence of parasites in sheep. The correspondents include not only other researchers but various Virginia farmers with whom Threlkeld worked. These folders contain correspondence, project reports, and notes. The collection also contains a folder of general research correspondence, as well as professional correspondence not directly tied to any specific research and administrative correspondence relating to Threlkeld's career, students, and retirement. Also included is a collection of Threlkeld's publications as well as files relating to his book, Some Nematode Parasites of Domestic Animals. These folders contain reprint requests, book orders, and business records and correspondence relating to the book's publication.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by topic, with personal materials generally preceding those relating to Threlkeld's professional activities.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Agricultural extension work; Agriculture; Faculty; Science and Technology; University Archives; University History; Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Contents List
- Personal correspondence, 1929-1971, n.d. (Box-folder 1-1-2)
- Awards and memberships, 1939-1972, n.d. (Box-folder 1-3)
- Military service, 1919-1943, n.d. (Box-folder 1-4)
- Biographical materials, 1929-1959, n.d. (Box-folder 1-5)
- Sigma Xi, 1929-1967 (Box-folder 1-6)
- Opinion letters and notes, 1952-[1974], n.d. (Box-folder 1-7)
- Opinion printed materials, 1937-1974, n.d. (Box-folder 1-8)
- Cattle parasite studies, 1938-1958, n.d. (Box-folder 1-9)
- Sheep parasite studies, 1934-1952, n.d. (Box-folder 1-10)
- Cobalt deficiency project, 1949-1953, [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-11)
- "An Observation on the Relationship of Cobalt Deficiency to Internal Parasites of Sheep," 1949-1956, n.d. (Box-folder 1-12)
- Phenothiazine, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 1-13)
- Soil and nutrition, 1946-1951, n.d. (Box-folder 1-14)
- Swine kidney worm project, 1956, n.d. (Box-folder 1-15)
- Wildlife and veterinary parasitology, 1934-1960, n.d. (Box-folder 2-1)
- Research correspondence, 1929-1969 (Box-folder 2-2)
- Professional non-research correspondence, 1955-1965, n.d. (Box-folder 2-3)
- Administrative correspondence, 1930-1972, n.d. (Box-folder 2-4)
- Extension work, 1930-1955, n.d. (Box-folder 2-5)
- Teaching materials, 1951-1965, n.d. (Box-folder 2-6)
- Speech drafts and background materials, 1931-1960, n.d. (Box-folder 2-7)
- Publications, 1928-1958 (Box-folder 2-8)
- Publication requests, 1934-1967, n.d. (Box-folder 2-9)
- Some Nematode Parasites of Domestic Animals - permission requests, 1950-1958 (Box-folder 2-10)
- Some Nematode Parasites of Domestic Animals - orders, 1958-1963, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 2-11)
- Some Nematode Parasites of Domestic Animals - business records, 1952-1960 (Box-folder 2-12)